<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The spirituall madman, or, A prophesie concerning, the King, the Parliament, London, the Army; of the admirable fulnesse, and compleatnesse, of the restauration, and satisfaction of all interests. / Written by VVilliam Sedgewick.</title>
            <author>Sedgwick, William, 1609 or 10-1669?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92868</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2391</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E477_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205532</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864884</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864884</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117116</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92868)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117116)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 76:E477[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The spirituall madman, or, A prophesie concerning, the King, the Parliament, London, the Army; of the admirable fulnesse, and compleatnesse, of the restauration, and satisfaction of all interests. / Written by VVilliam Sedgewick.</title>
                  <author>Sedgwick, William, 1609 or 10-1669?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb 20th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117116:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Spirituall Madman, OR, A PROPHESIE CONCERNING, The <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Parliament, London,</hi> the <hi>Army;</hi> of the admirable ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and compleatneſſe, of the reſtauration, and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of all Intereſts.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>VVILLIAM SEDGEWICK.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed in the Year,</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:117116:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117116:2"/>
            <head>The SPIRITUAL MADMAN, OR A PROPHESI, CONCERNING THE KING.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Army is a particular part of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and that temporary, and occaſionall; and is by the bright ſhining of the Sun of <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> melted into a generall peace and unity; but lying under a particular condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, it ſhall receive a particular diſcharge. And we know thy imployment is ſo irkſome and unpleaſant to thee, To be the kingdomes Gaoler, to keep War in, and peace out; or to ſtand <hi>in the way to the Tree of life, with a flaming ſword;</hi> to keep men from the injoyment of their Liberty, KING, Peace; though thou art commanded to it by God (theſe things being yet forbidden the people,) yet thou wilt be glad to be releaſed from it; that thou and all other may come into the Paradiſe of God, and feed together upon the fruit of Divine peace and love.</p>
            <p>There is under thy aſſuming power over the Kingdome, <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> and all; and in thy maintaining thy Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ary power above, and againſt the Civill; in thy ſeeking thy owne ſubſiſting, and attempting to be the <hi>Kingdomes</hi> Lord &amp; reſtorer: The <hi>Lord</hi> cloathing himſelfe with zeal, as with a garment, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſing himſelfe about with flames of fire: <hi>A Man of War: a Lord of Hoſts:</hi> Caſting away his Fatherly Government, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Nations rebellion in all parts againſt himſelfe, and ruling us with a Rod of Iron. God marching before us, out of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117116:3"/>Egypts ſlavery, into a Wilderneſſe; turning us from a Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment into a Wilderneſſe; &amp; incamping in the mideſt of us, &amp; adminiſtering Lawes to us; <hi>as at Sinai:</hi> in thundering and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, clouds and darkneſſe; ſo rerrible, that makes all tremble: A <hi>yoke that neither we, nor our Fathers are able to beare:</hi> And ſo we ſee Gods ſeverity, under mans iniquities: And becauſe it is the Lords Rod, we kiſſe the Rod, and love you for it.</p>
            <p>Death is proper for this adminiſtration: The <hi>Lord our Husband,</hi> the Law dies; we were bound to honour you ſo long as you lived in the power and goodnes of God; The whole Kingdom bowed before you; while you led us ſafely through the Wildernes; But <hi>Moſes</hi> cannot bring us into <hi>Canaan;</hi> but muſt only have a <hi>view of it,</hi> and dye at <hi>mount Nebo:</hi> This power is weak through the fleſh, and cannot do it; if you contend now to effect any thing, it is but the Devil ſtriving <hi>for the body of Moſes,</hi> you are labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to ſet up an honourable carcaſſe; or to call back life into a dead body: Chriſt did come into it, and hath offered it up in his owne body, and naild this power faſt to the Tree; you are dead, fixt to the tree of ſhame, by the curſe with your Lord; and by death you ſhall overcome more then ever you overcame by life; ſubmitting to death, your wils, reaſons, luſts; your ſeeking a worldly Kingdome; your deſire of Lording it over others by force of armes, with all your projects, are ſlaine; and all enmity in you againſt others, and others againſt you.</p>
            <p>Death hath <hi>Disbanded</hi> you; eaſd you of your helliſh &amp; wrathful imployment: Reconciled you to all, and all to you; brought you from being Turkiſh Janiſaries, to bee <hi>Engliſh men:</hi> You are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved into a body of love; into GOD: you lye downe in the Eternall.</p>
            <p>By this your arreares are paid; you are nothing, you are dead, and you can require nothing; you, and your demands are fallen to the ground; your ſervice is dead, and nothing is due to it, but to be buried, and all your miſcarriages, in forgetfulneſſe. Who do you require arreares of? The Kingdome is dead; the ſword reignes, and therefore the Kingdome is free: if you will be paid; take <hi>blood, want, ſpoile, Confuſion, ruin:</hi> that's all that is left of the <hi>Kingdome;</hi> pay your ſelves of that. Do you expect it of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117116:3"/>
               <hi>Parliament?</hi> That is dead too. Poore Parliament, you have eat it up your ſelves in greedineſſe of pay, you tore her bowels out; and you can have no more.</p>
            <p>But all anger is paſt, there remaines nothing but love: you are dead, and live with Chriſt: come forth of your graves; ſtand up in the reſurrection of the Chriſt, in union and fellowſhip with Chriſt. <hi>The Lords hoſt;</hi> now the Lord is in you; and you pitch your tents about the Lord; and are the arme of God, ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out for his own defence, and for the puniſhing of tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors living in the ſtrength and Spirit of the Lord: and now, mighty and powerfull to execute divine pleaſure: Now you are under the <hi>Captain of our ſalvation;</hi> and at one intereſted in the ſalvation of the <hi>Nation;</hi> and of Chriſt, our Saviour</p>
            <p>Now we can pay you arreares: you never ſtuck upon arreares till you ſunk into the earth, into poor earthly mindes; riſe you again into ſpirit, you will count it your honour to help <hi>England freely:</hi> Money and a Saviour, cannot ſubſiſt together. That Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt that once acted in you to let go the Priſoners, <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands freedome and juſtice,</hi> without <hi>price or reward:</hi> that ſpirit ſhall revive in you: and then you will ſcorn to be mercinary.</p>
            <p>I know you diſdaine to keep <hi>Englands</hi> wounds open to ſuck her blood: you have hazarded your lives for juſtice and freedom, and can't now inſiſt upon pay: you are worthy your ſelves, and have the worth of all with you: if you deſire pay, enter with us into <hi>Canaan.</hi> and you ſhall have <hi>Vineyards that you planted not; wels that you diged not: A land flowing with milke and honey;</hi> ſuch mercies and bleſſings as you could not expect: The Lord is Judge, he will <hi>audite</hi> your accompts, and pay all that he owes you: Religion flouriſhing in the purity of it; peace and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe as Rivers and Seas; the ſweet, holy, unmoleſted enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your <hi>own</hi> families and eſtates, in the preſence and under the <hi>government</hi> of the moſt high: You ſhall now ſubſiſt in our <hi>bowels,</hi> be diſſolved into the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Kingdome,</hi> which is the beloved of Chriſt: <hi>Terrible as an Army with banners:</hi> terrible to the world, and the God of the world: to the Prince of darkneſſe: and ſo we ſhall disband you into ſpirit and power; the whole Nation ſhall be Souldiers <hi>able to draw the ſword of the ſpirit againſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117116:4"/>all forraign power;</hi> amongſt our ſelves wars ſhall ceaſe from the earth: you muſt beat your <hi>ſword into plow ſhares, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſpears into pruming-ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kes:</hi> to your honeſt trades again; there will need no Iron or ſteely wrath, but to plow up your own hearts, and to cut down enemies within your own breſts. All our Towns and Cities are gariſoned with a heavenly hoſt, and we have ſalvation for our walls and bulwarks; <hi>we ſhall lye down in peace, and none make us afraid:</hi> while we need force we ſhall uſe you, but not in civill wars, you muſt be removed, and only imployed in ſervice againſt ſtrangers: if you delight to ſit down by the ſtill ſtreames of <hi>Englands</hi> peace, and feed in our green paſtures of eternall love, you ſhall: if your valour makes you deſirous of military acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, we ſhall find enemies abroad to imploy your ſwords a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt: and when you undertake ſuch expeditions the Lord ſhall goe with you: you ſhall have Angels ſpirits that ſhall make you invincible where ever you goe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Levellers</hi> grew out of the Army, and are again ſhrunk into the Army, and therefore we will now joyne you to the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, being mingled together. In your endeavour to impoſe your <hi>Democracy,</hi> your <hi>popular</hi> Government upon the Kingdome; over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing &amp; overcurning all powers into the People: <hi>We hear the voide of one crying in the Wilderneſſe</hi> (<hi>England</hi> is become a Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe) <hi>all fleſh is graſſe</hi> (all power is corrupt) the Spirit of the Lord hath blowne upon it and its withered: This is <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> that exalts the vallies and brings down the hils: he brings all into the waters the People; God is in theſe Levellers caſting the Mountains into the depths of the Seas, plunging all into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed People; not ſuffering one ſtone to lye upon another.</p>
            <p>Thy place is to be in the Wilderneſſe, and not to come into the City: to expire and dye ſpeedily, to decreaſe, that he that comes after may increaſe: Thou art beheaded, thy devices are fallen to the <hi>ground,</hi> a <hi>muſhrome,</hi> thou wert little, and art nothing. <hi>What went you out to ſee? A reed ſhaken with the wind:</hi> growing out of the <hi>mire</hi> of the Nation: <hi>or a man clothed with ſoft rayment?</hi> People got into Kings houſes. In this ſtate thou art vaniſht, loſt, and raiſed in the ſpirit of Chriſt, the divine and eternall love of God: and in this Kingdom there is a perfect Levell: The People the originall of the Parliament and King, by a free giving
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117116:4"/>up themſelves and their Eſtates to the Parliament and King, are in the King and Parliament, and fully partake of the royalty and power of both; and are leveld with it: The people give honour and glory to the King, and ſo higher then he, or he their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject: He that gives, is greater then he that receives: Heer all the people are one with that ſpirit that is <hi>kingly</hi> that Anointing that makes <hi>Chriſt King:</hi> and ſo called <hi>mine Anointed</hi> living all in the liberty of that ſpirit that makes Kings: and are moſt perfectly content in the Kings greatneſſe, being that which themſelves conſtitute: making it themſelves, they live in it and enjoy it: And the King is levelled to the people by his ſufferings or humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and by his love taking in every Subject to himſelf: humbling of himſelf, to be but the Kingdoms Servant, and wearing his Crown only for the happineſſe and good of the people, living together, and brought into one body, head, and member. The e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall love is the <hi>Leveller,</hi> Divine Charity that lifts not up it ſelf, but is lifted up; and being lifted up, drawes all after it.</p>
            <p>I rejoyce in the healing thy breaches, oh <hi>London,</hi> thou honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable City: Thy iniquities have been great, there is a righteous one under them that will carry them without the City as a ſcape Goat into the wilderneſſe: we ſee the Lord in thee in thy greateſt filth; in thy violent enforcing powers above thee to thy own mind, in conſtraining the Parliament to thy will, by bold Petitions urged with tumults: we ſee darkened and ſhadowed the interceſſion of the Son of God, who with violence wreſts from his Father favour for himſelf and his people: he comes with boldneſſe to take what he asks, and ſaies, <hi>I will;</hi> and the power that Saints have in Chriſt <hi>to command God in prayer.</hi> In thy ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with the Parliament againſt the King, and thy free powring forth thy ſelf for her: We ſee the exceſſive love of Chriſt to his Church, who is raviſht with love, and for her forgets all things elſe: In thy ingroſſing the riches of the Kingdom into thee; thou are a ſhadow of Chriſt, who treaſures up wealth and riches of glory in the City of God for ur.</p>
            <p>But thy glory is gon, thy true life; the beautifull preſence of God hath left thee; and thou art burning in flames of wrath, jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, envies, diviſions: thou art waſted into a <hi>ſceleton;</hi> thy trade obſtructed by Sea and Land; thy People filled with rage, thy
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117116:5"/>bowells pained with fierce conteſts of parties, pulling various wayes; quite reſtleſſe, an unquiet Sea, in continuall agitation. The Lord dyes in thee, the Lords delight; thou wert his ſpouſe: thy glory and greatneſſe, it was the Lords; he ſuffers in thy ſuffering, and is covered in thy aſhes; lyes under the burthen of all thy wants, is pierced with the neceſſities of the poor: And thou art in the duſt of confuſion; a ruinous heap, the ſeat and place of vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, lying in a thick cloud of darkneſſe. But his fire purifies thee; in theſe flames thou loſeſt thy filthy pride, covetouſneſſe, malice, revenge, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt not periſh utterly; <hi>The voice of God is heard in thee</hi> to revive thee: thou ſhalt be built again: <hi>Thy foundation ſhall be all of precious ſtones,</hi> &amp;c. The glory of God ſhall ſhine in thee, thou art now the City of God; a righteous City: this is thy name, <hi>The Lord is there:</hi> The Lord diſplaies his glory in the midſt of thee: <hi>The new Jeruſalem</hi> in deed, in truth, in ſpirit, in perfect uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God; a heaven, and ſo in union amongſt your ſelves; <hi>Peace within thy walls, and plentiouſneſſe in thy palaces:</hi> a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at unity in it ſelf; there ſhall not be the leaſt found of diſcord in thee: Thy nature is love, light and holineſſe; <hi>The City of the great King:</hi> made happy by the preſence of the <hi>King,</hi> and all the <hi>state</hi> and <hi>honour</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom:</hi> Now open thy arms of <hi>Divine love,</hi> and take into thy imbraces the glory of <hi>England, Kings, Princes, Nobility, Gentry, Miniſtry, Iudges, Lawyers, with all the wiſdom, juſtice, power and excellency of heaven and earth;</hi> let all flock together; in one God, one Chriſt, one ſpirit, one City, and thouſands of thouſands of Saints and Angels dwelling in thee. Nothing ſhall be heard in thee but mirth and joy in the Lord our God; praiſes of the great <hi>King: Open thy gates, thy everlaſting doores, that the King of glory,</hi> the Lord of Hoſts, with all his hoſt of Princely powers, <hi>may enter in:</hi> And all the riches of the world ſhall ſlow into thee in thy trade, naturally, and abundantly: the wealth of both <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dies,</hi> and all parts, ſhall ſeek unto thee, and offer up it ſelf to ſatisfie thee: thou ſhalt be crowned with bleſſings; all contents and pleaſures ſhall continually run down thy ſtreets, and all in the ſight and face of the holy God; in the pure River of life.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:117116:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>All the works of God are perfect, found out of all them that take pleaſure therein:</hi> The greateſt and higheſt, are reſerved for us, in this later, and great <hi>day of God;</hi> wherein it pleaſeth the Lord to appear in his fulleſt, and moſt excellent glory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this of <hi>Englands</hi> ſalvation is a ſweet bud of it; a little taſte of that infinite Majeſty that is now breaking forth, in the glorious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ppearing of God. In this buſineſſe, the Lord ſatisfieth his own Intereſt, who is <hi>Alphis, and Omega, the firſt. and the laſt:</hi> and this is the root of our pleaſure <hi>that thou art pleaſed,</hi> and ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>Thou <hi>reigneſt,</hi> thou art <hi>King:</hi> this is thy due, all power and dominion is thine; tis thy right to have all, all are thine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for thee they were created &amp; made, <hi>King,</hi> Parliament, Lords, Commons, Miniſters, People, all ſorts, all ſides, all parties are the Lords, and thou wilt reign over and in all: from Sea to Sea, from one end of the Earth to the other, as <hi>lightening, ſhining</hi> from <hi>Eaſt</hi> to <hi>Weſt:</hi> ſo is thy <hi>Kingdom;</hi> and thy <hi>glory</hi> is now due to thee, that thou ſhouldeſt appear not in weakneſſe to ſerve men, but in thy <hi>great Majeſty,</hi> in thy higheſt honour thou muſt now ſhew forth plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thy ſelf in thy utmoſt and <hi>moſt enlarged goodneſſe,</hi> power and wiſdom; <hi>Nothing</hi> now will ſerve thee but to be <hi>all in all:</hi> To be <hi>all</hi> thou art in Heaven, <hi>in all</hi> the Earth, to bring forth <hi>all</hi> thy riches to ſill every creature, <hi>all glory</hi> in <hi>all things:</hi> Thou art all in Earth as well as all in Heaven, all in King, in Parliament, in People, there is nothing but thy ſelf in theſe, thou art Biſhops, Presbyters, Independents, all theſe, and all in theſe; all Majeſty, power, glory, juſtice, in the King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and all the ſame in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and all that too in the people<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thou art all the labour, ſtrength, riches, freedom in the People, all this in the Parliament, all the ſame in the King, all hight and all lowneſſe: Thou art all Wiſdom, Authority, Government in Biſhops; all care zeal, labour in Presbyters, all love union, abſoluteneſſe in Independents: and all theſe in every one; thou art the ſame in all <hi>all in all:</hi> All in darkneſſe all in light, all in weakneſſe, all in ſtrength: all that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very part is all the whol is, all the whol in every part: and all Heaven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all Glory, all peace, all quietneſſe, all love, all goodneſſe in all theſe parts and whol: Leſſe then this generall and near uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and <hi>mariage</hi> will not ſatisfie thee; being thy ſelf ſatisfied, thou
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117116:6"/>doeſt ſatisfy all; and being pleaſed, thou pleaſeſt all: thy content, contents every one, becauſe thou art all: art content it ſelf in all.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt <hi>ſhaken all Nations, and the deſire of all Nation is come:</hi> We have been ſhaken into peeces, and every peece ſhaken out of all order and peace. Thou art good that thou doeſt but ſhake only; renders, that thou maiſt make way for thy ſelf to enter &amp; for all to enter with thee into every part. What we deſire, we have: we can deſire nothing but the Lord, nothing is deſirable but the Lord; <hi>the Lord we have,</hi> and in the Lord we meet with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very deſirable thing <hi>the deſire ſatisfied, which is a tree of life.</hi> God was our deſire, which is now interpreted; being brought forth into performance and enjoyment: God the bottom and top; the deſire, and deſired, meeeing in one ſpirit and Kingdom; God the root in our deſires, grown up into the fruit, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment.</p>
            <p>The <hi>intereſt of this whole Kingdom, in this reſtoration, is ſathfied;</hi> and that conſiſts in; firſt, PEACE, a ſure <hi>Peace,</hi> a wel-grounded <hi>Peace:</hi> here you have the richeſt jewell of <hi>peace</hi> that heaven hath; the <hi>Peace of God:</hi> The union and agreement of Father, Son, and Spirit in one; this is our peace, and a wel-grounded peace, ſetled and ſure; that is laſting and durable; a threefold cord that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be broken.</p>
            <p>We are one with God, reconcil'd to Godf; we dwell together in the ſame houſe; he hath married us, one in God, one as God; one amongſt our ſelves, as he is one: All in the Father, the Head, the KING; all in the Son, the Body, the <hi>Parliament:</hi> All in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in combination; acting and living together in their juſt and lawfull rights; and in <hi>perfect fruit of righteouſneſſe, love and peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The Nation deſires SETTLEMENT, after her ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, heres everlaſting Settlement, upon ſure foundations; <hi>The ſure mercies of David;</hi> upon the rock of ages: he <hi>who was, is, and ever will be:</hi> thoſe pillars upon which <hi>England</hi> ſtood, made clear, and bright; and the Kingdom ſetled upon them: Now <hi>the world is eſtabliſht</hi> in eternity, ſo <hi>that it cannot be moved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, The <hi>HONO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ROF THE NATION:</hi> honoured in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; For <hi>glory doth dwell in our Land;</hi> our <hi>Nation</hi> now <hi>is the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117116:6"/>very throne and ſeat of Divine glory, a Royall Nation;</hi> filled with Princely ſpirits: the <hi>Kingdom it ſelf</hi> raiſed from the <hi>grave</hi> of luſts, luxury, covetuouſneſſe, oppreſſion, baſeneſſe and beaſtlineſs, into the <hi>nobleneſſe and wiſdom of the ſpirit of God: England</hi> firſt brought forth into that excellent and perfect <hi>righteouſneſſe, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and juſtice</hi> that ſhall be a copy to other Nations; a <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> that ſhall bring forth <hi>ſalvation to all the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, The SETLING OF RELIGION; of the <hi>true Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox, ancient Proteſtant Religion;</hi> and the <hi>rooting out Sects, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, popery:</hi> This doth it compleatly and fully. We now ſhall have <hi>ſound doctrin,</hi> meaſured by the <hi>ſcripture of truth, the golden line</hi> of truth it ſelf: truth derived from the <hi>bowells of eternity,</hi> and conſtantly preſerved and kept in the <hi>worſt ages,</hi> free from defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <hi>giving teſtimony of it ſelf</hi> ſucceſſively in the darkeſt times, and now breaking forth in undeniable; and in diſputable autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and evidence: Not peeces but a whole body of Divinity; Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity it ſelf; not in ſhadow, but the body of it; not maim'd but intire and whole, from the higheſt head and glory of God, to the loweſt part of hell: and all the variety of eſtates, <hi>in Chriſt, in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, in men;</hi> with their fallings and riſings, deſcendings and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendings, fully and plainly brought forth. The Sun ſhall ſhine ſo clearly, as ſhall diſcipate theſe miſts of error that are amongſt us; with ſuch power as ſhall compoſe the madneſſe and diſorder of peoples judgments, into a beautifull Uniformity; <hi>by power of the Spirit of God, and in ſatisfaction to every mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, Another publick intereſt is, <hi>LIBERTY</hi> from all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing powers, this we have here reſtored; <hi>a glorioue liberty,</hi> in which all <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> ſhall live under Authority as children, not ſervants nor ſlaves; ſome ſhall rule as Fathers, others ſhall obey as Sons: Nothing but <hi>love, goodneſſe, and gentleneſſe in both;</hi> both to command and obey, ſhall be ſweet and delightfull: no Laws but the perfect Law of liberty, which the ſubject ſhall chooſe and deſire. A KING <hi>free and inlarged into the hearts and eſtates of his people; living in all they are and have, and they pleaſed to have it all the Kings; every one hating that which will not be the</hi> KINGS, <hi>and Common-wealths;</hi> counting that baſe and unworthy, that is not every ones as well as his own; and that only to be rich, which is free for all: and ſo men free to part with, as well as to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117116:7"/>injoy; eſtates free as well as perſons; and men <hi>not ſlaves to men, nor to their wealth:</hi> no, not to <hi>propriety;</hi> which is the greateſt bondage to ſerve themſelves, and their own wealth: That's true wealth, <hi>Common wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the People <hi>free, living in the boſome of the</hi> King; <hi>in his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and greatneſſe:</hi> they have a true right to it, as they have to any thing; <hi>The Court is their Fathers houſe;</hi> the <hi>Thro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> their own home; where every ſubject dwels, and lives in the <hi>Kings honour and preſence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixtly, <hi>In this we have</hi> A right underſtanding <hi>between King</hi> and <hi>Parliament:</hi> The wiſdome of God to ſhew us a <hi>way of peace; the true light</hi> ſhining from heaven upon us: the <hi>night</hi> of our miſtakes <hi>is paſt; The princes of darkneſſe is thrown down;</hi> and we are <hi>tranſlated out of a kingdom of darkneſſe, into the Kingdom of God;</hi> in which we ſhall alwaies have the <hi>true wiſdom to guid us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly, Here likewiſe have we AN ACT OF OB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIVION, whereby all tranſgreſſions <hi>are blotted out; all car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried into the depth of the Sea:</hi> where <hi>ſinne,</hi> if it be ſought for, <hi>it ſhall not be found:</hi> ſuch a fulneſſe of pleaſure and ſatisfaction, as will not admit <hi>a thought of revenge;</hi> if we ſhall remember paſt things, it will be with joy and thanks to each other; for in hurting, we have ſaved one another: wherein we have done evill to any, it is turned to their good; The KING will thank the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> for riſing againſt him; and the <hi>Parliament</hi> thank the KING for leaving of them: There is GOD, and perfect good in <hi>all</hi> that every party hath ſuffered.</p>
            <p>HAPPINES <hi>it ſelfe; England</hi> now hath a confluence of the riches of Heaven and Earth in one bleſſedneſſe: <hi>England; a glorious Land;</hi> the Land of God; abounding in ſtore, trade, juſtice, peace, amity. We are fallen,, but (as hath been expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted) <hi>WE RISE AS ONE MAN: England</hi> acted by one head, one ſpirit, is become <hi>one man:</hi> every one <hi>loving</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as himſelfe; and <hi>riſing</hi> againſt the COMMON ENE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MY, the Devill, the Deſtroyer; who is, and hath been our on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enemy; we hate none but him: and by this RISING, we free our ſelves from him.</p>
            <p>As this ſatisfies the <hi>publick,</hi> ſo every <hi>particular intereſt,</hi> or <hi>all intereſts are here ſatisfied,</hi> and brought into one <hi>intereſt,</hi> which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117116:7"/>is the <hi>true nature of an intereſt;</hi> to be in others <hi>a joynt, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſubſiſtence:</hi> every part made cleane and right, and <hi>ſo inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weaved</hi> into one <hi>intire garment; which is the excellency of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine works,</hi> they are large and ſave all; that's a humane and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villiſh deſigne, <hi>that ſaves one by the ruine of another;</hi> but that is Gods way to ſave all ſo, <hi>as the ſalvation of one is the ſalvation of another:</hi> Now here you ſee all contented.</p>
            <p>The KING (as all have ſworn and prayed) advanced in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to honour and greatneſſe; freed from priſon, <hi>from chaines of darkneſſe</hi> wherein he hath been held; brought out of a low <hi>dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon of wrath</hi> and <hi>heavie affliction,</hi> to the <hi>highest Throre of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty:</hi> Perſon, and Office reſtored from blackneſſe and foulneſſe, to <hi>ſplendor and brigheneſſe,</hi> into the Majeſtie of God; and that performed which the Parliament often promiſed, A GLO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIOUS KING; a KING in the <hi>glory of God;</hi> or the <hi>glorious God;</hi> the Immortall KING <hi>Reigning in man, and over men: Sir,</hi> this is your true Intereſt; its your life and ſoule; I know tis your heart, though yet <hi>lying his:</hi> Tis the Key will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock your ſpirit, and bring it cut into the light and liberty of God; unlock your underſtanding, after <hi>ſeven times</hi> have paſſed over you, you ſhall returne to your <hi>Threne,</hi> and true Majeſty ſhall be given to you; and your <hi>Nobles and Kingdomes</hi> ſhall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour you; all ſhall freely bow to you; and you ſhall command &amp; <hi>Reigne</hi> againe, to the terrour of your adverſaries, and joy of your friends: now the <hi>Priſon doores ſtand open to</hi> you, and you ſhall returne to your <hi>Royall Parliament</hi> and <hi>City</hi> after ſeven yeares baniſhment.</p>
            <p>We have now a King in whom we can confide, as in <hi>God;</hi> now the LORD lives in him, tis impiety and wickedneſſe to have a thought of diſtruſt concerning him; the <hi>ſure juſtice and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of God</hi> in habits in the Throne, as its propet place.</p>
            <p>We have a King according to our own hearts; he lives in our hearts; ariſes out of our hearts; and our hearts give him his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion: he hath all we have, and hath not too much, becauſe he hath us too; and nothing but what we freely give: one <hi>high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er by the head then all the People:</hi> having the wiſdome of the whole in him; of the largeſt underſtanding, and therefore King becauſe he doth in true worth excell any in the Nation, and is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117116:8"/>of all men fitteſt to <hi>reign:</hi> fitted by his <hi>great ſuffering,</hi> and Gods fulneſſe dwelling in him.</p>
            <p>This is the <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EENS intereſt</hi> ſhe may return to the King, there is no feare now, ſhe cannot hurt either Parliament or <hi>Religion,</hi> both being in ſuch a condition as cannot be hurt: beſides living in this <hi>light,</hi> of <hi>all</hi> ſhe ſhall moſt love the Parliament; It being the ſame with her ſelf the <hi>Kings Conſort,</hi> &amp; ſhe being the ſame with it, concurting together in ſeverall wayes to help, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the King: if ſhe ſhould attempt any thing againſt it it would be <hi>againſt the King and her ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Parliament adminiſtring about the affaires of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that the <hi>King may enjoy his Queen and Family</hi> with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt plenty, honour, eaſe and pleaſure: and the <hi>Queen admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring</hi> in the domeſticall affaires of the <hi>King</hi> about his Perſon, <hi>that the King may enjoy his Parliament and people in greateſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and freedom:</hi> The Parliament in buſineſſe of State, a <hi>Queen</hi> lying in the boſome of the <hi>King; and the Queen</hi> in private and perſonall affaires a Parliament: and ſo Parliament and Queen intereſted, ioyn'd in one intereſt; And for her <hi>religion</hi> we are now ſo far from being afraid of it, that we rejoyce in it, and in her great intereſt in the Papacie: For as the Papiſts had by her <hi>deſigns upon us:</hi> ſo now <hi>(the ſtream being turned)</hi> we ſhall by her <hi>deſign upon them,</hi> and over-run the whole Papacie with <hi>light and truth,</hi> ſhe ſhall be the <hi>doore</hi> by which we ſhall enter into all the riches and honours of the Papacie, and without injurie to them, we ſhall ſpoile them of all their <hi>glory, or rather bring a glorious fire amongſt them, that ſhall out ſhine theirs; and burn up theirs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Prince</hi> his <hi>Intereſt</hi> is here ſatisfied, he is indeed one <hi>with the Parliament; they and he are brethren deſcended both from the loyns of the King,</hi> and are one in various forms: each being the glory of the <hi>King,</hi> ane the ſtaffe of his age, <hi>Chriſtened</hi> at the ſame <hi>Font</hi> the Spirit of Chriſt: both the hope and joy of <hi>England,</hi> both being the glory of the King, propagated unto eternity, a never failing off ſpring, and flouriſhing in the vigour and youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of the Son of God: both intereſted into Chriſt, or the <hi>intereſt</hi> of Chriſt, and ſo of each other.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Lords</hi> who have loſt their Nobility, ſunck in diſgrace, ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117116:8"/>and almoſt buried in diſhonour; by this ſhall be reſtored, not to airy empty Titles, but to true Nobility: The Lord doth appear Lord of Lords, your Lord, owning Lordlineſſe, and filling of it with himſelf, as well as King of Kings, and as he ſets a Crown of pure gold upon the head of the King: ſo Coronets of pure gold upon yours, you ſhall ſhine as ſtars in this Firmament, in wiſdom, holineſſe, juſtice and goodneſſe, and be in affinity to the King the head; ennobled with heavenly Majeſty, fit to be about the Throne, and advanced to be the ſhoulders and breſt of the Nation, next the head.</p>
            <p>The Kings party are here fully ſatisfyed: to ſee their <hi>King</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to the honour and greatneſſe of his Anceſtors, his Proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitors: which is into the glory of God the great King, the Kings true Father: They that contend for known Lawes, by this the Laws are known by God, brought out of the duſt of the earth, in which they were trampled upon, and reſtored into the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and life of God: And now we ſhall ſee the whole body of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Lawes interpreted and opened to us by the wiſdom of God, and all drawn forth into life and power by the ſpirit of God, as we ſee the fundamentall Law of King and Parliament, written in the face of God and Chriſt by the Spirit.</p>
            <p>You ſhall have Religion in the old way, in the good old way, Divine ſervice; wherein every part of it ſhall be irradiated with the Beames of Divinity, and in every thing you ſhall ſee the face of God, and have fellowſhip with the Divine nature: Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſhall be adorned with ſolemnity, State, Pomp, Glory, Eaſe, Muſick, all Heavenly and Earthly together, ſuch as may allure and pleaſe the minds of men, and there ſhall be nothing harſh or rude in it: yea, rudeneſſe it ſelf ſhall have its comlineſſe. You ſhall have your ſports, pleaſures, <hi>we will fing together in the hight of Zion: young men and maids dannce together</hi> without offence or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity, all in the innocency, holineſſe and joy of God: your whol life a courſe of pleaſure; all things, yea labour and pains ſhall be recreations: God recreating all things, or making all things new, they ſhall be ſweet and delightfull: you ſhall have yout Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, yea, your whole life ſhall be ſpent in Holy-dayes, a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall reſt, the great <hi>Jubile.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:117116:9"/>
            <p>You the more civill and ſolid of that party, that ſinck into a retired condition in theſe tempeſtious times, that lye quietly and patiently in your graves of your own and the Kingdoms ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; your reſurrection is come, and you ſhall revive, and in a new ſpirit act for, and in the proſperity of the Nation.</p>
            <p>And you mad Lads ſhall ſweare: <hi>Now the Lord lives in truth, righteouſneſſe, and judgement,</hi> and know him preſent with you; <hi>ſweare</hi> by the <hi>eternall God,</hi> the ſpirit filling every Oath with truth: you ſhall curſe your enemy the Devill with all plagues to the pit of hell, and ſo dam him and ram him in, that he ſhall no more come forth to trouble you: you ſhall eat and drink freely, and forget <hi>your ſelves and your ſorrow,</hi> and in it be filled with the ſpirit of the Lord: be raiſed into high mirth and jollity, drink ſo freely of this <hi>new wine of the Kingdom,</hi> till you are drunk out of your own wits into the Princely ſpirit of God, and then ever ſpeak and act things of love, worth, bravery, and excellency: This is the KINGS HEALTH, his <hi>ſaving health,</hi> his union with God, God with him, <hi>drink</hi> of this health freely: and the whole Kingdom ſhall PLEDGE; be bound to <hi>fill it again,</hi> and drink down this heavenly liquor of the Majeſty of <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>King</hi> into them: and the whole people ſhall ſay, and <hi>ſee it performed,</hi> GOD SAVE THE KING: The King is ſaved in God; <hi>and God the ſalvation of the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This reſtoration fully ſatisfies the Parliaments <hi>Intereſt,</hi> gives her higher <hi>Priviledges:</hi> She is called to an honourable ſtate to live in the <hi>Lord Chriſt,</hi> to ſit with <hi>Chriſt in heavenly places,</hi> to be one with the Son, the body of God: to be <hi>Jer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſalem</hi> above the mother of us all; and therefore <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee,</hi> free with God, and in God with the King: freedom to enter into his heart and boſome, to lye there continually: <hi>The King ſhall greatly deſire they beauty;</hi> Thou now haſt power as wel as liberty, to make righteous Laws in perfect Righteouſneſs that ſhall ſtand for ever: ſuch a King and ſuch a Parliament as we have long beg'd to agree together in juſt things: and in both we ſhall reap the fruit of our prayers: which though they were <hi>ſowed in weakneſs,</hi> and now ſeem dead and rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the earth, yet ſhall <hi>riſe in power.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
